<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
<title>Hunter Lockwood&#039;s Website</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/</link>
<description>Latest Changes &amp; RSS Feed</description>
<language>en</language>
<item>
<title>About</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/about/</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 09:21:45 -0400</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hunterlockwood.github.io/about/?1729603305</guid>
<dc:creator>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</dc:creator>
<description>Professionalia I work in the Language Research Office at The Myaamia Center under Dr. David Costa. The Myaamia Center is the Miami Tribe of…</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="professionalia">Professionalia</h2>

<p>I work in the Language Research Office at <a href="https://miamioh.edu/myaamia-center/">The Myaamia Center</a> under <a href="https://miamioh.edu/myaamia-center/about/staff-faculty-affiliates/costa/index.html">Dr. David Costa</a>. The Myaamia Center is <a href="https://miamination.com">the Miami </a><a href="https://www.bia.gov/tribal-leaders/miami-tribe-oklahoma">Tribe </a> <a href="https://miamination.com/">of Oklahoma's</a> research center on Miami University's campus in Oxford, Ohio.</p>

<p>I finished my Ph.D. in Linguistics at the University of Wisconsin-Madison in August 2017. Under the supervision of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monica_Macaulay">Dr. Monica Macaulay</a>, my dissertation, <a href="https://www.proquest.com/docview/1957409352"><em>How the Potawatomi Language Lives: A Grammar of Potawatomi</em></a> translates the name the elders gave <a href="https://shop.fcpotawatomi.com/products/potawatomi-dictionary/">The Forest County Potawatomi Dictionary</a>, which I helped compile and edit while I was in graduate school.</p>

<div class="notice3">
<div>
<div>
<p>🤔 If you want to know more about what I do, check out my <a href="/about/research.html">research</a> page, or check out <a href="/about/selected-writings.html">a selection of what I have written</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Research</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/about/research</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 09:19:46 -0400</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hunterlockwood.github.io/about/research?1729603186</guid>
<dc:creator>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</dc:creator>
<description>My focus for many years has been to contribute to the documentation &amp; reclamation of Algonquian languages, especially Miami-Illinois &amp;…</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My focus for many years has been to <strong>contribute to the documentation &amp; reclamation of Algonquian languages, especially Miami-Illinois &amp; Ojibwe-Potawatomi</strong>.</p>

<p>As a part of the <strong>Language Research Office at <a href="https://miamioh.edu/myaamia-center/index.html">The Myaamia Center</a></strong>, I work in Oxford, Ohio, to support the <strong>Miami Tribe of Oklahoma</strong> in their efforts to revitalize their language. Recently, much of the public-facing scholarship I do can be considered <em>digital philology</em>, in that I work with textual sources. <a href="/about/selected-writings.html">Check out some of my work</a> for more information.</p>

<p>Less visibly, I work closely with the other Offices at the Center, supporting the <a href="https://aacimotaatiiyankwi.org/education/programming/">pedagogical &amp; educational efforts</a> of the Miami Tribe of Oklahoma and <a href="https://miamioh.edu/myaamia-center/research/digital-resources/index.html">the software development team</a>, who is responsible for the <a href="https://ilaatawaakani.org">Indigenous Languages Digital Archive</a> (ILDA) and other digital resources.</p>

<h2 id="algonquian-language-documentation-for-language-reclamation">Algonquian Language Documentation for Language Reclamation</h2>

<p>My research interests have never been limited to a single subfield or theoretical approach. In fact, that's what drew me to language research in the first place; anytime you're ever learning about anything, there's language involved<a href="https://www.etymonline.com/word/ineffable">...more or less.</a></p>

<p>In graduate school, I was influenced heavily by a quote that I can never find the source of; the way I always recite it is this, and it's how I try to live:</p>

<div class="notice1">
<p>Language documentation is too valuable to waste on linguists alone.</p>
</div>

<h3 id="things-i-tend-to-think-about"><em>Things I tend to think about</em></h3>

<p>I have written on and consulted about a variety of topics in linguistics. The list below ought to give an idea of the range of my interests and what I've been thinking about recently.</p>

<div class="notice2">
<div>
<p><strong>kihkintoolilo</strong> 'take note!'</p>

<p><em>I work for myaamiaki people.</em> If you're myaamia and you have a question about something,  <a href="/contact">get in touch</a> and I'll see what I can do!</p>
</div>
</div>

<ul>
<li>🗣️<em><strong>Phonology</strong></em>: The study of sounds as a system; syllables &amp; prosody; phonotactics; historical and comparative phonology.</li>
<li>🧱<em><strong>Morphology</strong></em>: Word structure; morphophonology, morphosyntax, historical and comparative morphology with <a href="https://nisinoon.net/">Monica Macaulay</a>.</li>
<li>🕸️<em><strong>Lexical Semantics</strong></em>: Word meaning, how words are related to each other &amp; the world; metaphors and metonymy; semantic change over time.</li>
<li>️👥<em><strong>Sociocultural linguistics</strong></em>: Identity; ideologies, attitudes and beliefs about language; phonoaesthetics &amp; iconicity; language variation.</li>
<li>🤖<em><strong>Computational linguistics</strong></em>: Software supporting language communities; natural language processing; ethics &amp; best practices; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Answer_set_programming">answer set programming</a> with <a href="https://miamioh.edu/profiles/cec/daniela-inclezan.html">Daniela Inclezan</a>.</li>
<li>🌎<em><strong>Linguistic Anthropology</strong></em>: Knowledge systems &amp; indigenous epistemologies, e.g.: 🧮 <em>ethnomathematics</em> (number systems &amp; measurement); 🌝 <em>ethnoastronomy</em>, (cosmology, constellations &amp; calendrics); 🫎 <em>ethnobiology</em> (classification and management of plants, animals &amp; ecosystems); 🗺️ <em>geolinguistics</em> (placenames &amp; landscapes).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="miami-illinois-language-reclamation">Miami-Illinois Language Reclamation</h2>

<p>At any given moment, I have several short- and long-term research projects in progress focusing on various aspects of what scholars call the
<strong>Miami-Illinois language</strong> — Miami-Illinois is an academic cover term for the languages spoken by Miami, Wea, Peoria, Kaskaskia, and other related groups of people in the southern Great Lakes region.</p>

<p>Today, most myaamia speakers refer to their language as <a href="/wiki/myaamiaataweenki">myaamiaataweenki</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/media/images/pano-miamiok.jpg" width="2937" height="1097" alt="Miami Nation Dance Grounds, Miami, Oklahoma" title="Miami Nation Dance Grounds, Miami, Oklahoma" class="rounded" /></p>

<h3 id="ilda-https-ilaatawaakani-org"><a href="https://ilaatawaakani.org"><em>ILDA</em></a></h3>

<p>Language projects often resemble what <a href="https://jan.ucc.nau.edu/~jar/ILR/">Keren Rice (2009) called "the two solitudes"</a>. More recently, I learned about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_law">Conway's Law</a>, which is the idea that organizations end up designing systems that reflect their own communication patterns.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://ilaatawaakani.org/">ILDA</a> platform unifies the analytical and pedagogical functions by recognizing them as distinct; it was built from the ground up with and for both user groups in mind. Data from the primary sources and secondary sources flow together to present information that is useful to different user groups.</p>

<p>It was originally designed specifically for the Myaamia Center's use case, e.g. easily making available annotations from manuscripts like <a href="https://mc.miamioh.edu/ilda-myaamia/documents/19">Jean-Antoine Robert LeBoullenger's</a> 18th century Miami-Illinois dictionary to today's team of speaker-learner-teachers</p>

<div class="notice3">
<div>
<div>
<p>The ILDA platform unifies the analytical and pedagogical functions by recognizing them as distinct.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>

<p>ILDA now can handle audio/video files marked up by <a href="https://archive.mpi.nl/tla/elan">ELAN</a> and is regularly used by Native American tribal language programs across the country for precisely this purpose.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="nisinoon-https-nisinoon-net"><a href="https://nisinoon.net/">Nisinoon</a></h2>

<p>Algonquian languages are known for complex words with many meaningful parts. Linguists typically divide these into three primary <a href="/wiki/word-guts.html">components</a>: an initial, a medial, and a final.</p>

<p><a href="https://nisinoon.net/"><strong>Nisinoon</strong></a> is <a href="https://ojibwe.lib.umn.edu/main-entry/nisinoon-vii">an Ojibwe word</a> that means <em>they are three; there are three of them</em></p>

<p>As part of an NSF-Funded grant project, my former dissertation advisor <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monica_Macaulay">Dr. Monica Macaulay</a> and I are working with <a href="https://danielhieber.info/">Dr. Daniel Hieber</a> to create <a href="https://nisinoon.net">nisinoon</a>, a tool to explore the structures of words in Algonquian languages.</p>

<p>Along the way, we created other resources like a <a href="https://nisinoon.net/bibliography">bibliography of Algonquian morphology</a>.</p>

<h2 id="ojibwe-potawatomi">Ojibwe-Potawatomi</h2>

<p>Ojibwe-Potawatomi is an academic cover term for a large group of varieties spoken on the northern Great Lakes region. For various analytical and ideological reasons, many of these languages either are or were sometimes known as "dialects of Ojibwe". Such appellations are imprecise and outdated.</p>

<p>My dissertation was a descriptive grammar of Potawatomi, marking the culmination of almost a decade of work with and for Anishinaabe people from different communities across the Three Fires but especially the Forest County Potawatomi Community.</p>

<p>It was designed to accompany the Forest County Potawatomi Dictionary <a href="https://www.neh.gov/sites/default/files/2018-06/potawatomi_documentation_lexical_database_and_dictionary.pdf">(<code>grant pdf</code>)</a>, which I also helped to compile, and contains a few stories that were collected as part of the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1263888">corpus project</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>myaamiaataweenki</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/wiki/myaamiaataweenki</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 09:17:29 -0400</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hunterlockwood.github.io/wiki/myaamiaataweenki?1729603049</guid>
<dc:creator>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</dc:creator>
<description>What is the difference between myaamiaataweenki &amp; Miami-Illinois? Miami-Illinois is what I call an academic cover term - it is a term that scholars…</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-the-difference-between-myaamiaataweenki-miami-illinois">What is the difference between <em>myaamiaataweenki</em> &amp; <em>Miami-Illinois</em>?</h2>

<p>Miami-Illinois is what I call an <em>academic cover term</em> - it is a term that scholars use to refer to a lot of different groups of people, without being specific. It's very useful, sometimes, to have generic words!</p>

<div class="notice1">
<p>Today, most speakers of the language call it <a href="https://mc.miamioh.edu/ilda-myaamia/dictionary/entries/6648">myaamiaataweenki</a>.</p>

<p>If you'd like to see what I've written about the language, check out <a href="/about/selected-writings.html">some of my writings</a>!</p>
</div>

<h3 id="ceekiši-iilaataweenkia-https-mc-miamioh-edu-ilda-myaamia-phrases-443757-all-kinds-of-languages"><a href="https://mc.miamioh.edu/ilda-myaamia/phrases/443757">ceekiši iilaataweenkia</a> <em>'all kinds of languages'</em></h3>

<p>What are the <a href="/wiki/word-guts.html">components (or "word guts")</a> of the word <em>myaaamiaataweenki</em>?</p>

<p>Obviously, <strong>myaamia</strong> is the name of the people. But how does the other part mean 'language'?</p>

<p><strong>-aatawee</strong> is a verb component. We sometimes call it a <em>no-object verb</em>, because, well, it doesn't take an object! (linguists would say it is <em>intransitive</em>)! When this piece appears in a word, it means 'speak a language', so we can use all the ordinary verb endings like <strong>myaamiaataweewaaci</strong> <em>they speak/are speaking the myaamia language</em>.</p>

<div class="notice1">
<p>That leaves <code>-(e)nki</code>, which is a <em>suffix (ending)</em> on no-object verbs that takes the subject away!</p>

<p>It's sort of like the verb <em>speak</em> &amp; the noun <em>speech</em> in English...</p>

<p>But it's more similar to Spanish sentences like <em>se habla Español</em> <em>Spanish is spoken</em>.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Presentations, Publications and Other Writings by Hunter Thompson Lockwood</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/about/selected-writings</link>
<pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 09:08:17 -0400</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hunterlockwood.github.io/about/selected-writings?1729602497</guid>
<dc:creator>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</dc:creator>
<description>A selection of my academic work is given below. I have given each work listed here a subjective rating of how relevant it might be to the sort of…</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A selection of my academic work is given below. I have given each work listed here a subjective rating of how relevant it might be to the sort of language learner who finds themselves reading linguistics papers. The rating scale is as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>😴 Marginal</code> indicates that the work focuses on a language other than myaamiaataweenki or is very technical.

<ul>
<li>This could be relevant to something you're interested in, but it might be in an indirect way or as background information.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><code>🦧 Low</code> indicates the work might be about multiple Algonquian languages or be focused on questions that aren't very relevant to most people.

<ul>
<li>It will be easier to get some value out of reading this, if you're only interested in myaamiaataweenki, but it might not be the most useful.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><code>🎯 High</code> indicates the work is primarily about myaamiaataweenki or otherwise has a lot of examples that could be useful to ordinary people.

<ul>
<li>These I hope readers can get use out of without knowing or caring about any of the linguistics.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="bringing-myaamia-kiilhswaakana-lunar-calendars-into-the-digital-age-2024">Bringing myaamia kiilhswaakana ‘Lunar Calendars’ into the Digital Age (2024)</h2>

<p>(with Kristina Fox)</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Short summary</strong> Presentation on the journey the myaamia lunar calendar has made, where it's going. This talk also covers some ethnoastronomical questions about leap months and cyclical time.</li>
<li><strong>Relevance to myaamiaataweenki learners</strong> 🎯 High

<ul>
<li><em>Target language</em> myaamiaataweenki</li>
<li><em>Useful examples</em> Numerous</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Availability</strong> After conference, I will post slides and handout here!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="temperature-expressions-in-the-miami-illinois-corpus-to-appear">Temperature expressions in the Miami-Illinois corpus (to appear)</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Short summary</strong> Paper investigating the expression of temperature in myaamiaataweenki. When I was first learning an Algonquian language, temperature expressions helped me understand how words worked, so it's a topic I revisit regularly or when learning a new language.</li>
<li><strong>Relevance to myaamiaataweenki learners</strong> 🎯 High

<ul>
<li><em>Target language</em> myaamiaataweenki</li>
<li><em>Useful examples</em> Numerous</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Availability</strong> <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1GuC4jm1CaGcyEjK23msoZFS9mYvtEw3o/view?usp=sharing">Prepublication version</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="applicatives-across-algonquian-2024">Applicatives across Algonquian (2024)</h2>

<p>(with Monica Macaulay)</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Short summary</strong> Paper surveying how applicatives work in Algonquian languages, which is linguistics jargon for a way of adding extra arguments to a verb. This is a chapter from an volume on applicatives edited by European typologists whose defintion of applicative slightly differs from what you might learn in an American linguistics class.</li>
<li><strong>Relevance to myaamiaataweenki learners</strong> 😴 Marginal

<ul>
<li><em>Target language</em> Algonquian family</li>
<li><em>Useful examples</em> Few</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Availability</strong>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110730951-018">Chapter 18 in <em>Applicative Constructions in the World's Languages</em></a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="notes-on-measurement-and-mathematics-in-miami-illinois-2023">Notes on measurement and mathematics in Miami-Illinois (2023)</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Short summary</strong> Presentation investigating the grammatical tools people used in myaamiaataweenki to measure things and do math. I spend a lot of time in this piece discussing the methodological challenges of interpreting obsolete measurement terms in the record (like "toise" and "cubit").</li>
<li><strong>Relevance to myaamiaataweenki learners</strong> 🎯 High

<ul>
<li><em>Target language</em> myaamiaataweenki</li>
<li><em>Useful examples</em> Numerous</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Availability</strong> <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1gx72vYMhwDg9IRymkbOhNWiSGXvsa1F5/view?usp=sharing">Slides</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="strategies-for-lexical-expansion-in-algonquian-languages-2023">Strategies for lexical expansion in Algonquian languages (2023)</h2>

<p>(with Rachel Fedorchak, Vade Kamenitsa-Hale, and Monica Macaulay)</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Short summary</strong> Paper comparing word formation patterns across the Algonquian family, based on a survey of over 150 words. Metonymy, part-for whole relationship, ends up being the most common strategy; new words arise from speakers naming what is most salient, most noticeable, most important.</li>
<li><strong>Relevance to myaamiaataweenki learners</strong> 🦧 Low

<ul>
<li><em>Target language</em> Algonquian family</li>
<li><em>Useful examples</em> Several</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Availability</strong> <a href="http://hdl.handle.net/10125/74735">Open Access</a> via <a href="https://nflrc.hawaii.edu/ldc/">Language Documentation &amp; Conservation</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="survey-of-content-questions-in-miami-illinois-2023">Survey of content questions in Miami-Illinois (2023)</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Short summary</strong> Paper investigating "content questions", which are the type of questions that are looking for information. In English, these are also called "wh-questions" because they start with words like "what" or "where".</li>
<li><strong>Relevance to myaamiaataweenki learners</strong> 🎯 High

<ul>
<li><em>Target language</em> myaamiaataweenki</li>
<li><em>Useful examples</em> Numerous</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Availability</strong> <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Yja9LBH23gSAqooifNBfqdrU9JglIj20/view?usp=sharing">Prepublication version</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="relative-roots-form-and-function-2023">Relative Roots: Form and Function (2023)</h2>

<p>(with Monica Macaulay and Vivian Nash)</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Short summary</strong> Presentation surveying relative roots, Algonquianist jargon for a part of word that connects the meaning of the verb to some other part of the sentence.</li>
<li><strong>Relevance to myaamiaataweenki learners</strong> 🦧 Low

<ul>
<li><em>Target language</em> Algonquian family</li>
<li><em>Useful examples</em> Few</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Availability</strong>

<ul>
<li>Currently unavailable. More on relative roots can be found in some of the other papers (e.g. the Applicatives paper, also comes up in the Measurement and Content Questions papers)</li>
<li>...I will happily write more specifically about relative roots in myaamiaataweenki if there's interest!</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="nominal-tam-and-the-preterit-in-potawatomi-2018">Nominal TAM and the Preterit in Potawatomi (2018)</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Short summary</strong> Paper detailing the usage of the preterit ending in Potawatomi and argues against the existence of so-called "nominal tense". The preterit is used differently than in myaamiaataweenki, but may still be useful if you're exploring the archival records.</li>
<li><strong>Relevance to myaamiaataweenki learners</strong> 😴 Marginal

<ul>
<li><em>Target language</em> Potawatomi</li>
<li><em>Useful examples</em> None</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Availability</strong> <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1iqFz2mJo7lQ_YFg_Irb0bSuNu1z-6F1l/view?usp=sharing">Prepublication version</a></li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Home</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 10:04:49 -0400</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hunterlockwood.github.io/?1717682689</guid>
<dc:creator>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</dc:creator>
<description>Hi there! My name is Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood (he/him), but most people just call me Hunter. I am a non-Native person; I took that picture a few…</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="hi-there-_"><em>Hi there!</em></h2>

<p><img src="/media/images/houghton_lake-high_summer.jpg" width="1140" height="400" alt="Puffy clouds populate a blue sky over the shores of Houghton Lake, Michigan, as viewed from out in the water" title="Puffy clouds populate a blue sky over the shores of Houghton Lake, Michigan, as viewed from out in the water" class="rounded" /></p>

<p>My name is <strong>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</strong> <code>(he/him)</code>, but most people just call me Hunter. I am a non-Native person; I took that picture a few miles from where I grew up, on land ceded by Anishinaabe people in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_of_Washington_(1836)">The 1836 Treaty of Washington</a>.</p>

<p>I am a linguist who works to support Native American people and communities through language <a href="/about/research.html">research</a>.</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="/feed/"><code>/feed/</code></a> to see what's new around here, or use a <a href="https://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification"><code>Really Simple Syndication</code></a> Feed Reader to follow all of your favorite internet websites using <a href="/feed/page:feed.xml">RSS links like this</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Florilegium</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/wiki/</link>
<pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 10:51:13 -0400</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hunterlockwood.github.io/wiki/?1717599073</guid>
<dc:creator>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</dc:creator>
<description>The word florilegium is a Latin calque, an old one, of Greek anthology. Both share the same metaphorical extension of the original meaning, in that…</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The word <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Florilegium"><strong><em>florilegium</em></strong></a> is a Latin <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calque">calque</a>, an old one, of Greek <strong>anthology</strong>. Both share the same metaphorical extension of the original meaning, in that they refer to large collections of short writings. Unlike <em>anthology</em>, however, <strong><em>Florilegium</em></strong> still retains the etymological sense <em>a gathering of flowers</em>.</p>

<p>I've collected some notes about how this came to be, under <a href="/wiki/rhizomes-replantings">Rhizomes and Replantings</a>.</p>

<p>I also have a few notes about <a href="/wiki/myaamiaataweenki">the Myaamia Language</a>.</p>

<h3 id="pages">Pages</h3>

<div class="wikipages">
<ul>
<li><a class="tag-myaamia tag-algonquiana" href="/wiki/myaamiaataweenki">myaamiaataweenki</a></li>
<li><a class="tag-algonquiana tag-myaamia" href="/wiki/obviative-circle">Who is in the Circle? Proximate and Obviative</a></li>
<li><a class="tag-algonquiana" href="/wiki/word-guts.html">Word Guts, Morphology &amp; the Internal Structure of Words</a></li>
<li><a class="tag-rhizome" href="/wiki/rhizomes-replantings">🍄Rhizomes &amp; Replantings🪴</a></li>
</ul>
</div>


<h3 id="tags">Tags</h3>

<div class="wikitags">
<ul>
<li><a href="/wiki/tag:algonquiana/">algonquiana</a></li>
<li><a href="/wiki/tag:myaamia/">myaamia</a></li>
<li><a href="/wiki/tag:rhizome/">rhizome</a></li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Who is in the Circle? Proximate and Obviative</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/wiki/obviative-circle</link>
<pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 18:14:04 -0400</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hunterlockwood.github.io/wiki/obviative-circle?1717452844</guid>
<dc:creator>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</dc:creator>
<description>myaamiaataweenki, like the other Algonquian languages, has two different forms of the noun depending on whether it is obviative or proximate. Laura…</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="/wiki/myaamiaataweenki">myaamiaataweenki</a>, like the other Algonquian languages, has two different forms of the noun depending on whether it is <em>obviative</em> or <em>proximate</em>.</p>

<p>Laura Welcher used a circle metaphor to explain the obviative:proximate contrast in Potawatomi. As far as I know, this was a teaching method that she did not widely publish, but some of the (now-deceased) Potawatomi elders were still cheerfully remembering and using this strategy decades later:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[A] circle was drawn for most sentences and the audience was asked to state the obviative within that message.<br />
  - <em>Potawatomi Traveling Times</em> 2016-08-15, 22(4):1 <a href="https://www.fcpotawatomi.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/August-15-2016.pdf">pdf</a>†</p>
</blockquote>

<div class="notice3">
<div>
<div>
<p><em>† The document linked above contains a photograph of person who has since passed away</em> (Viewing images of people who have died is a violation of some Indigenous religious beliefs).</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>

<h2 id="summary-table">Summary Table</h2>

<p>Here's a table, showing the different forms in myaamiaataweenki.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th>Meaning</th>
  <th><code>[proximate]</code></th>
  <th><code>[obviative]</code></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://mc.miamioh.edu/ilda-myaamia/dictionary/entries/3083">🐕</a></td>
  <td><strong>alemwa</strong></td>
  <td><strong>alemwali</strong> or <strong>alemooli</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://mc.miamioh.edu/ilda-myaamia/dictionary/entries/3083">🐕🐕</a></td>
  <td><strong>alemwaki</strong></td>
  <td><strong>alemwahi</strong> or <strong>alemoohi</strong></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>In some of the Algonquian languages, there are no obviative plurals anymore. But <a href="/wiki/myaamiaataweenki">myaamiaataweenki</a> still has them!</p>

<hr />

<p>...so how do they work? What do you do with them?</p>

<h2 id="using-obviative-and-proximate-in-conversation">Using Obviative and Proximate in Conversation</h2>

<p>That's where the circle comes in! There can only be <em>one</em> (1) proximate in a sentence; all other animates have to be obviative.</p>

<p>Think of it this way: <em>conversations and stories aren't limitless</em>. We can only keep track of so many things at one time.</p>

<p>So to help us keep track of what we're talking about, imagine a circle. The circle has just enough room for me/us (<code>1st person</code>), you/y'all (<code>2nd person</code>), and one other animate noun (<code>3rd person</code>) .</p>

<p>The 3rd person you decide to bring into the circle is <code>proximate</code>. All the rest, the ones you leave out, are <code>obviative</code>.</p>

<p>But don't take my word for it...</p>

<h3 id="examples-from-speakers">Examples from speakers</h3>

<p>Compare this sentence, where <strong>alemooki</strong> is the only one in the circle...</p>

<div class="notice1">
<p><strong>neehi <em>alemooki</em> meekišiweeciki</strong></p>

<p>'and dogs bark'
<a href="https://mc.miamioh.edu/ilda-myaamia/phrases/11828">Trowbridge 367-13-1</a></p>
</div>

<p>...with this next one, where there's not enough room in the circle for everyone. The speaker who LeBoullenger recorded 400 years ago decided to leave <strong><a href="https://mc.miamioh.edu/ilda-myaamia/dictionary/entries/3308">kwaahkwaanihsia</a></strong> 'grasshopper' out, and make it an obviative:</p>

<div class="notice1">
<p><strong><em>kwaahkwaanihsiahi</em> eemwaaci</strong></p>

<p>'he eats grasshoppers'
<a href="https://mc.miamioh.edu/ilda-myaamia/phrases/271948">LeBoullenger 376-56-1</a></p>
</div>

<p>The grasshoppers don't fit in the circle, because the person doing the eating is the one we're talking about, and he's already there!</p>

<h2 id="so-what">So what?</h2>

<p>You might not use it right now, but this ending gets used in the stories a lot...because most of the time you have to talk about more than two people to tell a story!</p>

<p>So if you haven't heard it yet or seen it before, keep your eyes and ears open - I bet you'll run into it soon!</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>🍄Rhizomes &amp; Replantings🪴</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/wiki/rhizomes-replantings</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 17:52:19 -0400</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hunterlockwood.github.io/wiki/rhizomes-replantings?1717278739</guid>
<dc:creator>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</dc:creator>
<description>🍄Rhizomes &amp; Replantings🪴 In what&#039;s plotted here, the following inspirations can be observed: The Zettelkasten &amp; Digital Gardening approaches Groups &amp;…</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="rhizomes-replantings">🍄Rhizomes &amp; Replantings🪴</h2>

<p>In what's plotted here, the following inspirations can be observed:</p>

<ul>
<li>The <a href="https://zettelkasten.de/introduction">Zettelkasten</a> &amp; <a href="https://maggieappleton.com/garden-history">Digital Gardening approaches</a></li>
<li>Groups &amp; movements that reflect my own, phantasmagorical memories of an Internet that used to exist, for example:

<ul>
<li><a href="https://geminiprotocol.net/">geminispace</a> and other alternative web protocols</li>
<li>...but see <a href="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2023/05/28/the-gemini-protocol-seen-by-this-http-client-person/">this blogpost by Daniel Stenberg</a>, creator of <a href="https://curl.se/"><code>curl</code></a>, for an excellent critique of geminispace</li>
<li><a href="https://indieweb.org/">indieweb</a> &amp; <a href="https://small-web.org/">small-web</a></li>
<li>comparable  movements in gaming, like <a href="https://www.technicalgrimoire.com/david/2019/06/sworddream">the SWORD DREAM</a>.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>A number of tools designed to process markdown, including:

<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_OneNote">OneNote</a>, which I stopped using a number of years ago but deserves honorable mention for years of service,</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Obsidian_(software)">Obsidian</a>, of course; I actually had a paid subscription for it, but I ended up wanting something sleeker and more minimal,</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/logseq/logseq?tab=readme-ov-file#-why-logseq">LogSeq</a>, an excellent FOSS competitor to Obsidian</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Contact</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/contact/</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 17:08:48 -0400</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hunterlockwood.github.io/contact/?1717276128</guid>
<dc:creator>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</dc:creator>
<description>📬 Electronic Mail This page will enable you to use the Simple Mail Transfer Protocol 📧 to send me Electronic Mail. Your Name: Email: Message: I…</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="electronic-mail">📬 Electronic Mail</h2>

<p>This page will enable you to use the <a href="https://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2821.txt">Simple Mail Transfer Protocol 📧</a> to send me Electronic Mail.</p>

<div class="contact">
<form class="contact-form" action="/contact/" method="post">
<p class="contact-name"><label for="name">Your Name:</label><br /><input type="text" class="form-control" name="name" id="name" value="" /></p>
<p class="contact-email"><label for="email">Email:</label><br /><input type="text" class="form-control" name="email" id="email" value="" /></p>
<p class="contact-message"><label for="message">Message:</label><br /><textarea class="form-control" name="message" id="message" rows="7" cols="70"></textarea></p>
<p class="contact-consent"><input type="checkbox" name="consent" value="consent" id="consent"> <label for="consent">I understand that clicking this button will send and store information on the Internet.</label></p>
<input type="hidden" name="referer" value="https://hunterlockwood.github.io/contact/" />
<input type="hidden" name="status" value="send" />
<input type="submit" value="Send" class="btn contact-btn" />
</form>
</div>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
<title>Word Guts, Morphology &amp; the Internal Structure of Words</title>
<link>https://hunterlockwood.github.io/wiki/word-guts</link>
<pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 13:59:00 -0400</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="false">https://hunterlockwood.github.io/wiki/word-guts?1717264740</guid>
<dc:creator>Dr. Hunter Thompson Lockwood</dc:creator>
<description>Backstory When I was helping put together the Forest County Potawatomi Dictionary, we spent a lot of time talking about language, and Lindsay Marean,…</description>
<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="backstory">Backstory</h2>

<p>When I was helping put together the <a href="/about/research.html">Forest County Potawatomi Dictionary</a>, we spent a lot of time <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metalinguistics">talking about language</a>, and Lindsay Marean, a Potawatomi woman who at the time was a linguist and is now also a programmer, shared a story with me about using the term <em>verb guts</em> with the elders and others when trying to talk about what linguists call <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morphological_derivation"><em>derivational morphology</em></a>, the study of meaningful sub-components of words.</p>

<p>I adapted this, here and elsewhere, extending it to <strong>word guts</strong>, for the simple reason that nouns also have guts!</p>

<h3 id="why-word-guts.html">Why <em>Word Guts</em>?</h3>

<p>Linguists sometimes talk about or display language in ways that community members find objectionable. Unusable language will be presented alongside impenetrable theoretical jargon.</p>

<p>People who study Ojibwe have been talking about this for a long time; that's why Rand Valentine's <em>Nishnaabemwin Reference Grammar</em>, for instance, displays example sentences without "cutting up" words.</p>

<p>But linguists like me still need to study these building blocks of words in order to understand the language better. The solution I try to follow is to be sure to present full, usable language alongside segmented, unpronounceable pieces (in my memory, credit for this idea goes to Wes Leonard, but I can't find a reference to it, offhand...).</p>

<h2 id="what-are-word-guts.html">What are <em>Word Guts</em>?</h2>

<p>Living things like humans are made up of internal organs; when separated from each other, neither of us can survive. We may look simple, on the outside, but internally, we are complex.</p>

<p>Living words are like this, too! Words are made up of smaller parts that, when separated from each other, don't make any sense &amp; can't survive.</p>

<div class="notice1">
<p>A <em>language</em> is a <em>type of knowledge</em>.</p>
</div>

<p>But instead of internal organs, linguists who study Algonquian languages like myaamiaataweenki and Bodwéwadmimwen sometimes say that words are made up of <em>components</em>. Components are the smallest parts of a word that do or mean something. Together, they make up the stable body of the word, which I call the <em>base</em> or the <em>stem</em>.</p>

<p>A language is a type of knowledge. Fluent speakers know and recognize thousands of different components of words! They use that knowledge to combine words in novel ways and to understand words they've never heard before.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
